Guide to the Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records, 1953-2000 MSS 1002
Heinz History Center
- State School and Hospital (SSH) and Interim Care Committee Records, 1972-1997; II.
  - State Schools and Hospitals (SSH) and Interim Care Facilities, 1972-1984; 4.
    - Highland Park Center Maladaptive Behavior Programming Correspondence, Reports, and Policies, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Letter from N. Karen Kelly to Walter Cohen, June 2, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 1)
        A letter from N. Karen Kelly, past president the ARC Allegheny County, to Secretary Walter Cohen of the Department of Public Welfare regarding ARC Allegheny's concerns about maladaptive behavior treatments at Highland Park Center, including the use of animal prods on residents.
      - Highland Park Center Report, May 27, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 2)
        The ARC Allegheny visitation team's report after a visit to Highland Park Center. The team addressed numerous issues, including the use of a cattle prod and restraints on residents.
      - Highland Park Center Maladaptive Behavior Program Progress Report, February 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 3)
        Dr. Mario Fischetti's report on maladaptive behavior treatment at Highland Park Center to the Board of Directors. Fischetti's includes his justification for the use of electroshock therapy in certain cases.
      - Memo from Peg Veedock to Highland Park Center Staff, January 25, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 4)
        A memo from Associate Executive Director of Highland Park Center Peg Veedock to the rest of the staff praising them after a review.
      - Highland Park Center Maladaptive Behavior Program Report, c. 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 5)
        A report to the Board of Highland Park Center by Dr. Mario Fischetti regarding external reviews of the institution's maladaptive behavior treatments. Fischetti notes that the center discontinued the use of electroshock treatment as a result.
      - Highland Park Center Program Services Department Status Report, January 27, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 6)
        A status report for Highland Park Center's Program Services Department by Millie Telega, assistant executive director for program services.
      - Highland Park Center Maladaptive Behavior Program Progress Report (2), April 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 7)
        A report to the Board of Highland Park Center by Dr. Mario Fischetti regarding concerns about the use of electroshock treatment at the center and the steps taken to evaluate the use of such treatment.
      - Letter from N. Karen Kelly to Dorothy Rowe, April 4, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 8)
        A letter from N. Karen Kelly, first vice president the ARC of Pennsylvania, to Dorothy Rowe of the Office of Mental Retardation listing recommendations for state institutions, including suggestions to improve programming and staff training.
      - Bob Nelkin Notes on Erik Wittman, September 30, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 9)
        Handwritten notes by Bob Nelkin after a meeting with Erik Wittman, leader of a Department of Public Welfare investigation into Highland Park Center.
      - Letter from Walter Cohen to N. Karen Kelly, June 27, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 10)
        A letter from Secretary Walter Cohen of the Department of Public Welfare to N. Karen Kelly, member of the ARC of Allegheny County, addressing concerns regarding the Maladaptive Behavior Program at Highland Park Center.
    - Highland Park Center Emma M.: Maladaptive Behavior Program, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Highland Park Center Research: Electroshock Therapy Maladaptive Behavior, c. 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Highland Park Center Photographs (Building Exterior, Electric Cattle Prod, and Restraints), 1983 (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - Highland Park Center Restraining Chair, August 1983 (Box 4, Folder 56, Item 1)
        An image of a chair with restraints used on individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities at Highland Park Center.
      - Highland Park Center Resident Helmet, August 1983 (Box 4, Folder 56, Item 2)
        An image of a helmet used on an individual with intellectual and developmental disabilities at Highland Park Center.
      - Highland Park Center Resident Helmet (2), August 1983 (Box 4, Folder 56, Item 3)
      - Highland Park Center Straitjacket, August 1983 (Box 4, Folder 56, Item 4)
        An image of a straitjacket used on individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities at Highland Park Center.
      - Highland Park Center Cattle Prod, August 1983 (Box 4, Folder 56, Item 5)
        An image of a cattle prod used to shock individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities at Highland Park Center.
    - Highland Park Center News Clippings, July 1983-February 1984, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Mountaintop School Report: Visitation, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - Findings of the ACC-PARC Review Team at Mountaintop School for the Mentally Retarded, October 20, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 58, Item 1)
        A report by the ACC-PARC Review Team detailing the incidents of abuse at Mountaintop School for the Mentally Retarded in Wapwallopen, Pennsylvania.
    - Pleasant Manor Correspondence Regarding Site Visit, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Ridgeview Center Correspondence Regarding Court Appearance, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - Letter from Donald Oesterling to Bob Nelkin, October 31, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 60, Item 1)
        A letter from Pennsylvania State Senator Donald Oesterling to Bob Nelkin offering the opportunity to testify to the State Senate in regards to the death of Louis Novak at Ridgeview Center.
    - Ridgeview Center News Clippings, August-October 1972 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Robinson Development Center Correspondence, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Slingsgrove State School and Hospital Correspondence Regarding Supplemental Security Income, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - Bob Nelkin Letter Regarding Supplemental Security Income Benefits at Selinsgrove State School and Hospital, March 30, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 63, Item 1)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin to the superintendent of Selinsgrove State School and Hospital inquiring about the institution's procedures regarding Supplemental Security Income and Social Security for residents.
      - Letter from Joseph Scartelli to Bob Nelkin, April 14, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 63, Item 2)
        A letter from Joseph Scartelli, superintendent of Selinsgrove State School and Hospital, to Bob Nelkin responding to his inquiries about the institution's procedures regarding Supplemental Security Income and Social Security for residents.
    - Stillmeadow School News Clippings, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Research, 1966-1981; 5.
    This series is comprised of research materials gathered and utilized by ACC-PARC members that supported their advocacy work in residential care facilities. The records in this series include research articles, exposés, and books pertaining to topics such as the right to live in community, institutional models, mental health services, citizen advocacy, resident deaths, inadequacies at institutions, and mental health conditions and abuses. Titles include Christmas in Purgatory, The Origin and Nature of our Institutional Models, and The Family Papers: A Return to Purgatory.
    - Publications and Exposes I, 1966-1975 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Publications and Exposes II, 1966-1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Publications and Exposes III, 1966-1975 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Publications and Exposes IV, 1966-1975 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Citizen Advocacy for the Handicapped, Impaired, and Disadvantaged - The President's Committee on Mental Retardation, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - MH/MR Articles, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Pennsylvania Residential Services Articles, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Advocacy Articles, 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Mental Health - Conditions and Abuse, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Program Analysis of Service Systems (MR), 1978 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - The Community Imperative: Refutation of All Arguments in Support of Institutionalization Anybody Because of Mental Retardation I, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - The Community Imperative: Refutation of All Arguments in Support of Institutionalization Anybody Because of Mental Retardation II, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - The Right to Live in the Community, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Publications: MR, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Notes: MR Treatment Models, Undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Research Articles, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Scrapbooks, 1966-1975; III.
  This series is comprised of three scrapbooks that document ACC-PARC activities and programs throughout the 1960s and 1970s. The first scrapbook documents ACC-PARC activities and initiatives throughout 1966-1967, including benefits, workshops, awards, fund drives, presentations, and advocacy efforts. In particular, this scrapbook highlights ACC-PARC efforts to raise public awareness of the abilities of people with disabilities to work. The second scrapbook dates to 1972 and is comprised of news clippings that document deaths of residents at the Ridgeview Center. The third scrapbook details the Melwood Preschool program (1974-1975) for the people with disabilities and includes class photos, class activities, and class field trips.
  - ACC-PARC Scrapbook, 1966-1967 (Shelf 1, Volume 1)
  - Pat Clapp Scrapbook on Hillcrest/Ridgeview Center, 1972 (Shelf 1, Volume 2)
  - Melwood Preschool Scrapbook, 1974-1975 (Shelf 1, Volume 3)
- Photographs, 1955-2000; IV.
  This series contains photographs that include portraits (ca1960s-ca1990s), group shots (ca1960s-ca1990s), PR images (1975-1986), award ceremony shots (1977-1988), and other event-related photographs. Events captured in these photographs include the Opportunity Center/PARC-Way initiative (1984-1998), the Avalon Group Home (1991), the ARC-Allegheny dedication (1998), and camp activities (2000).
  - Portraits, c. 1960-1990 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Group Shots, 1955-1990 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Press Photographs, 1975-1986 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Awards, 1977-1988 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Opportunity Center/PARC-Way, 1984-1998 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Avalon Group Home, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Dedication Celebration, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Camp Activities, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 24)